Welcome to this tutorial on Gradient Descent, one of
the most important optimization techniques in machine learning.
In supervised learning, we often want to find the parameter set
theta star that minimizes some objective function J of theta.
When the objective function is too complex for closed-form
optimization, or when the parameter dimension is huge, we
turn to iterative methods like gradient descent.
Intuitively, imagine J of theta as a terrain. Gradient descent starts
from an initial point, looks for the steepest downward direction, takes
a small step, and repeats until it reaches a minimum.
In this tutorial, we'll explore gradient descent
in four stages: One-dimensional gradient descent, extension
to many dimensions, application to regression, and
finally stochastic gradient descent for large datasets.
Let's start with gradient descent in one dimension.
In the one-dimensional case, we have three hyperparameters: the
initial value theta init, the step size or learning
rate eta, and an accuracy threshold epsilon.
Here's the algorithm for one-dimensional gradient descent.
Let's see an example with the function f of x equals x minus
2 squared, starting at x equals 4 with a learning rate of 0.5.
Now, let's run through a few iterations
of gradient descent with step size 0.5.
We've converged to the minimum at x equals 2 in just one step
because this is a quadratic function and our step size was optimally chosen.
For convex functions like this one, gradient descent converges to
the global minimum if the step size is small enough.
However, if the function is non-convex, convergence depends on the
starting point and step size. Gradient descent can get stuck
at saddle points or diverge if no minimum exists.
Now, let's extend gradient descent to multiple dimensions.
When the parameter theta is in R to the
m, the gradient becomes a vector of partial derivatives.
The gradient descent update becomes: Theta t equals Theta t minus 1
minus eta times the gradient of f at Theta t minus 1.
Let's visualize gradient descent in two
dimensions with a simple quadratic function.
In multiple dimensions, we follow the negative gradient at
each point, which is the direction of steepest descent.
For termination, we typically use a function change
threshold, where we stop when the absolute difference
between consecutive function values is less than epsilon.
Now, let's apply gradient descent to
linear regression with squared error loss.
For linear regression, our objective function is the
mean squared error between predictions and true values.
The gradient of this objective with respect to theta is given by:
Which leads to the update rule:
For ridge regression, we add L2
regularization to the objective function.
This gives us the following gradients for theta and theta zero:
Let's visualize how gradient descent works
for a simple regression problem.
Finally, let's look at stochastic gradient descent, or SGD.
When our objective function is a sum over many
data points, computing the full gradient can be costly.
Stochastic gradient descent updates using only one
randomly chosen term at each step.
If the objective is convex and the learning rate sequence satisfies
specific conditions, SGD converges to the optimum with probability 1.
There are several reasons to use SGD. First, it's more efficient
for large datasets, as each step only requires one data point.
Second, the noise in SGD updates may help escape
shallow local minima that would trap batch gradient descent.
Finally, SGD's slight under-optimization can reduce overfitting,
often leading to better generalization performance.
Let's compare the trajectories of batch gradient descent and SGD.
Let's summarize what we've learned about gradient descent.
Gradient descent is an iterative optimization algorithm that minimizes
an objective function by following the negative gradient direction.
It requires setting a learning rate,
initial parameter values, and stopping criteria.
The algorithm generalizes from one dimension to multiple dimensions,
making it applicable to a wide range of problems.
It can be applied to various machine learning
problems, such as linear and ridge regression.
For large datasets, stochastic gradient descent provides an efficient
alternative by using random subsamples of the data.
Thank you for watching this tutorial on gradient descent!